<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Anshuman Pandey - articles</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/feeds/articles.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://pandey.github.io/unicode/</id><updated>2014-01-05T15:39:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Anshuman Pandey</subtitle><entry><title>A “New” Khojki Inscription</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2014-01-05-new-khojki-inscription.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2014-01-05T15:39:00-08:00</published><updated>2014-01-05T15:39:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2014-01-05:/unicode/posts/2014-01-05-new-khojki-inscription.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s sort of a reverse Rorschach Test: if I see
a blank slate, my mind will fill it with orthographic 
imprints. Usually ethereal calligraphy, more recently, 
translucent epigraphy. I&amp;#8217;ve always marvelled
at the craftsmen who meticulously engrave complex scripts upon 
marble facades and copper plates; bringing a blank …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s sort of a reverse Rorschach Test: if I see
a blank slate, my mind will fill it with orthographic 
imprints. Usually ethereal calligraphy, more recently, 
translucent epigraphy. I&amp;#8217;ve always marvelled
at the craftsmen who meticulously engrave complex scripts upon 
marble facades and copper plates; bringing a blank slate 
to life with visible language. I recently had a chance to 
materialize my orthographic&amp;nbsp;fantasies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early December 2013, I attended an
open house at Equinox Studios in the Georgetown neighborhood of
Seattle. The artists had flung open the doors
of their studios for the public to experience
the spaces where inspiration meets the workbench. 
In one space an artist swung a wrecking ball into massive, ornate glass 
sculptures. In another, iron-wrights lit up the sky with 
pyrotechnic displays emanating from giant, intricate lattices 
and delicate cut-metal trees. While watching these 
industrial artists cast light and sound into the night, a 
more silent performance in one corner of the studio caught my&amp;nbsp;ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked over I saw stacks of sandstone blocks 
and people hunched over tables. I peered over the shoulder of a 
couple and saw them carving the logo of the
Seattle Seahawks into one of these blocks. A few feet away, 
metal workers fed wood into the blazing mouth of a 
furnace. I watched as a pair of workers reached into the furnace 
with a heavy metal yoke and extracted a crucible filled with 
bubbling liquid. Another worker collected finished blocks with 
carvings and placed them on a metal rack resting upon a bed of
black sand. At her signal, the bearers of the crucible inched
over to the rack and steadily poured the molten liquid into each
block. Further along the perimeter, a worker cracked the cooled 
blocks to release a metal tile, each bearing an 
embossed image of what has been etched into the&amp;nbsp;block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was engrossed by this process of sandstone etchings being
formed into pictographs on steel and nearly forgot about the
rest of the open house. Some of my companions wandered onto the
other installations as I grabbed a sandstone block and 
found a spot at the table. I began thinking about what 
I would want to see wrought in steel. Luckily, my friend 
saved me from writer&amp;#8217;s, um, block by exclaiming
&amp;#8220;Oh, write my last name in&amp;nbsp;Hindi!&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next 45 minutes I stood hunched over my block,
sketching her name first in pencil, then lightly tracing it with a
carving tool, then going over the grooves repeatedly until the
depths reached a quarter of an inch. Then the devil of details
arrived and he sat on my shoulder as I tried to coax the stone
to yield curves that resemble those of inked letters. When
I finished, I brushed off my shoulder and handed the finished
block to my friend, who ran her finger over the grooved of the
etched imprint of her name in reverse. Thumbs up. She passed it
onto the metal worker, who sprayed it with a graphite coat and
set it on the rack. We watched as the two crucible bearers
arrived with a fresh trove of molten steel and poured it onto
the&amp;nbsp;carving&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience at Equinox loomed in my mind. I still wasn&amp;#8217;t 
sure what I wanted to see cast in metal. A few days later it 
struck me while I was researching variant letter-forms used in
Khojki manuscripts while listening to Raageshwari Loomba&amp;#8217;s
rendition of the Ismaili &lt;i&gt;ginan&lt;/i&gt; &amp;#8220;Aaye Rahim Raheman&amp;#8221; by
Imam Begam. I read the &lt;i&gt;ginan&lt;/i&gt; in a printed Khojki book earlier in
the&amp;nbsp;month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/aaye_rahem_raheman_khojki.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if I could reproduce the
letter-forms that Laljibhai Devraj had cut in Germany in 1903
for the first ever Khojki metal types, which he used at his
Khoja Sindhi Printing Press in Bombay. I thought it
might be nice to do an etching of &amp;#8220;Aaye Rahim Rahman&amp;#8221;, the
&lt;i&gt;ginan&lt;/i&gt; which inspired me to think about a Khojki etching
in the first place, but that seemed a bit ambitious. After all,
I had only done one etching. So, I thought of the next best
thing I would want to etch in&amp;nbsp;Khojki&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, I would need my blank slate. My friend contacted
Alair Wells, a talented sculptress and metal artist, whose
studio &lt;a href="http://tinderheartmetals.com/"&gt;Tinder Heart
Metals&lt;/a&gt; at Equinox was hosting the metal working during the 
open house. I described my idea to Alair, who was excited 
to help. We produced a wooden cast for the block by
using four 2&amp;#8221; x 4&amp;#8221;s and affixing it to a plywood board. Then
Alair cut an 8&amp;#8221; x 10&amp;#8221; block from a pine board and we fixed that
to the plywood. We poured Washington grade 7 white silica into
the cast to measure the amount of sand we would need. Then
after we placed the silica into a bucket, Alair and my
friend mixed a catalyst and bonding agent into it, mixed
vigorously for minutes, and then poured the preparation into the
block. The 25 lb. sandstone block turned out&amp;nbsp;beautifully:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" class="image-process-article-image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/02_silica_block_with_tools.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I had my blank slate. Then, I chose my tools: 
a &lt;span class="st"&gt;⅜&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; nib, a &lt;span
class="st"&gt;⅛&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; nib, and a needle point:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/08_tools.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step was to sketch out the Khojki text using a pencil.
The text must be etched as a mirror image so that the embossing
on the tile will have the correct orientation. I had thought of
making a stencil by printing out the Khojki text in reverse and
cutting out the letters using a fine blade, but the glyphs of
the only Khojki font I have do not possess the sort of modulated
strokes I desired for the etching. So, I decided to do a free
hand rendering of the text in&amp;nbsp;reverse:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/03_pencil_sketch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then performed an initial etching. I held my breath quite a
bit during this part. Unlike writing on paper or composing in
typesetting software, you really cannot &amp;#8216;erase&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;undo&amp;#8217; an
erron without having extra
silica and bonding agent on hand. I lightly scraped the &lt;span
class="st"&gt;⅜&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; nib over the sketch I&amp;nbsp;made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/04_etching_started.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the etching of the upper portion of the block
is shown below. The grooves are shallow. I would eventually
deepen the&amp;nbsp;routes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/05_etching_finished.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then time to sketch out the text for the bottom portion of the
etching. I could have sketched out the entire text first, but I
had a feeling that my palm would just smudge the&amp;nbsp;graphite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/06_more_sketches.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the first run of the&amp;nbsp;etching:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/07_all_etched.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the broad nib for the text of the upper portion. It 
produced a very pleasant width and modulation that
resembled the style of Khojki I wanted to&amp;nbsp;emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/09_broad_nib_line.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Etching the tail of a vowel sign:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/10_broad_nib_modulation.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the bottom portion, I used the medium&amp;nbsp;nib. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/11_small_nib_line.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the needle point to take care of the small details, like
the dots and the terminals of&amp;nbsp;letters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/14_needle_hook.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on the&amp;nbsp;details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/12_needle_line.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was concerned about the size of the dots. I feared that if I
spaced them too closely, then the molten metal might just
obliterate the sandstone in between and I&amp;#8217;d end up with a blob
instead of three&amp;nbsp;dots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/13_needle_dots.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the before picture of the silica&amp;nbsp;block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/01_silica_block.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the after&amp;nbsp;picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/16_final_etching.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a close up of the text: &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/17_final_etching_face.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the morning of New Year&amp;#8217;s Eve, I returned the finished block
to Alair, who did another pouring in Tacoma that evening. This
is how it turned&amp;nbsp;out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/18_metal_etching.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly the best Khojki text to fill that blank&amp;nbsp;slate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was I developed my proposal for encoding Khojki in Unicode in
2009, I was contacted by Irfan Gowani, who was enthusiastic
about the future encoding. We spoke intermittently, but I did
not meet Irfan until I returned to Seattle in 2013. During the
past year Irfan and his wife Shelina have become wonderful
friends of mine. They are inspirational, creative, and lovely
people. And they are damned good cooks. One evening, a few days
before Christmas, as I left their home after dinner Shelina
handed me two jars of homemade quince and fig jam, sourced from
the fruit of their own trees. Apart from the kababs they feed
me, this was yet another testament of their giving nature. It
got me to thinking: what in the world could I offer them as an
expression of my&amp;nbsp;friendship?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else would express my gratitude for their
presence in my life more uniquely than an 8&amp;#8221; x 10&amp;#8221; x&lt;span class="st"&gt;
¾&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; metal plaque weighing 17 lb, which bears the names of
their family embossed in Khojki by my own hands?! I have yet to
present it to them. But, I have a feeling that it will always remind 
them of me&amp;#8230; especially whenever they need to move&amp;nbsp;it&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas and Happy New Year, Irfan and&amp;nbsp;Shelina!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;āye rahem rahemān, ab to rahem karoge,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;āye rahem rahemān, ab to rahem&amp;nbsp;karoge.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;ejī tana mana dhana guru ne arpaṇa kīje&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;to gināne gināne ginān, ab to rahem karoge.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;ejī dāna sakhāvat har dam kīje, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;to dāne dāne dān, ab to rahem karoge.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;ejī saba ghaṭ ekaja rahemān kīse,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;to śāne śāne śān, ab to rahem karoge.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;i&gt;ejī kahet īmām begam merā pīr hasan shāh,&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;īmāne īmāne īmān, ab to rahem&amp;nbsp;karoge.&lt;/i&gt;</content><category term="articles"/></entry></feed>