<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Anshuman Pandey - unicode</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/feeds/unicode.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://pandey.github.io/unicode/</id><updated>2014-05-09T16:43:39.794000-07:00</updated><subtitle>Anshuman Pandey</subtitle><entry><title>Gujarati signs for transliterating Arabic</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2014-05-09-gujarati-arabic.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2014-05-09T16:43:39.794000-07:00</published><updated>2014-05-09T16:43:39.794000-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2014-05-09:/unicode/posts/2014-05-09-gujarati-arabic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Usage of new diacritic marks in Ismaili&amp;nbsp;orthography&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ismaili communities such as the Ithnashari Khoja (&amp;#8220;Twelver Shia&amp;#8221;) and Agakhani Khoja 
use a convention for transliterating Arabic into the Gujarati script. The 
convention allows for the representation of Arabic letters and signs for which 
there are no corresponding characters in Gujarati. The diacritics used in 
the convention are written with Gujarati letters that mostly closely 
approximate the Arabic sound being represented. 
The creation of the full set and the first documented printing of
these signs was undertaken by the Ithnashari Khoja publisher Gulāmalī Ismāʾil of
Bhavnagar, Gujarat in 1901. The characters are now standard elements of the 
Gujarati orthography used by these communities.
Some of these diacritics are shown below, with 
color coding added, in an excerpt of a printed version of the Qurʾān in the 
Gujarati&amp;nbsp;script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/gujarati_arabic.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve written a &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n4574.pdf"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; 
to encode these characters as combining signs in the Gujarati block of the Unicode 
standard. I am interested in communicating with users about these and other signs 
used in Gujarati for similar purposes. Thank you to Iqbal Akhtar for informing me 
about these&amp;nbsp;signs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="gujarati"/></entry><entry><title>Siddham headstroke: abode of the inherent vowel?</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-11-15-siddham-headstroke.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-15T12:54:53.127000-08:00</published><updated>2013-11-15T12:54:53.127000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-11-15:/unicode/posts/2013-11-15-siddham-headstroke.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Native Japanese analysis of the Indic inherent&amp;nbsp;vowel&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The below excerpt from the &lt;em&gt;Shittan Hidenki&lt;/em&gt; [悉曇祕傳記] (&lt;em&gt;Taishō Shinshū Daizōkyō&lt;/em&gt;, 
vol. 84, no. 270) of Shinpan [信範] shows an analysis of independent vowel letters, 
their dependent forms, and the combinations of these dependent forms with the Siddham 
consonant letter &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KA&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_myoten_inherent_a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also shows a horizontal stroke associated with Siddham vowel letter A that correlates 
with the dependent forms of the other vowel letters. In Japanese, this stroke is known as 
the ア点 &lt;em&gt;a-ten&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; mark&amp;#8221; and is considered to be an elongated form of the 命点 
&lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;life mark&amp;#8221;. The &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; is the initial brush stroke used in the writing 
of all Siddham letters. The &lt;em&gt;a-ten&lt;/em&gt; is produced by extending the &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; to the right. 
It is not a true vowel sign; it is the headstroke of each consonant&amp;nbsp;letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hunch is that the concept of the &lt;em&gt;a-ten&lt;/em&gt; was developed by Japanese 
scholars as a way of explaining 
the inherent vowel /a/ possessed by every consonant letter. All Indic vowels 
have both independent and dependent forms, except for the letter A, which has only an 
independent form. The &lt;em&gt;a-ten&lt;/em&gt; raises several philosophical questions regarding the 
sound and forms of letters: How does one capture this inherent sound, which is part of the 
phonetic identity of each consonant letter, but which is graphically unmarked? Is it contained 
somehow in the letter form? If so, where in the glyph does it reside? As it represents the 
initial brush stroke used for writing the vowel letter A, it may be said to contain the graphical 
and phonetic essence of the&amp;nbsp;letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I raise the matter of the Siddham &lt;a href="https://pandey.github.io/posts/2013-11-13-siddham-myoten.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;em&gt;a-ten&lt;/em&gt; because it is significant from an ideographic perspective, as are the other 
elemental strokes identified in pedagogical texts. I am 
currently investigating the potential of encoding these elemental strokes, which I 
mentioned in my Siddham proposal as being out of scope for the basic encoding. I 
welcome any information on the &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; from users familiar with its philosophical 
interpretations and its use in Siddham&amp;nbsp;pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- toscheNovember 16, 2013 at 2:08 PM

In Japan, Siddham writing survived much more strongly than Sanskrit speech (which stopped 
rather quickly after Japan stopped trade with India), so I don't think ア点 and 命点 are 
important in terms of phonetics. Looking at Siddham books in Japan, I can find that almost 
all strokes have their own names (obviously the most important of all is ア点). So I agree 
with you; I think they were named so because the Japanese monks needed to develop terminology 
in order to teach writing, and found that this stroke is found in every letter.

As most of the books that discusses Siddham mention ア点 and 命点 in the text, it may be nice 
to have it encoded.

--&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="siddham"/></entry><entry><title>Siddham myō-ten: the essence of a character?</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-11-13-siddham-myoten.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-13T12:46:06.879000-08:00</published><updated>2013-11-13T12:46:06.879000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-11-13:/unicode/posts/2013-11-13-siddham-myoten.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes on analysis of Siddham character&amp;nbsp;strokes&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short downward sloping horizontal stroke is shown in some historical
and modern Siddham handbooks in connection with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIDDHAM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; A. In
&lt;em&gt;Sacred Calligraphy of the East&lt;/em&gt; (1981), John Stevens calls it a
&amp;#8216;variation&amp;#8217; of the vowel letter&amp;nbsp;A:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_myoten_variation_stevens.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the excerpt, below, from the &lt;em&gt;Zusetsu Bonji&lt;/em&gt; [図說梵字] (1974) of Kijun
Tokuzan [徳山暉純], the stroke is shown as a form of the vowel letter A,
on par with the dependent forms of the vowel letters A, I, and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_myoten_tokuzan.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giryū Kodama [児玉義隆] also shows it as a form of A in his &lt;em&gt;Bonji Hikkei&lt;/em&gt;
[梵字必携]&amp;nbsp;(1991):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_myoten_kodama.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it is correlated with Siddham vowel letter A, it is not a
true vowel sign, but represents the initial brush stroke used in
writing the vowel letter. Below is another excerpt from Tokuzan
(1974), which shows the nine brush strokes used for constructing the
vowel letter A, with the initial stroke&amp;nbsp;highlighted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_myoten_stroke_order.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same stroke is used in the creation of all
Siddham letters. The stroke is shown below in the forms for Siddham
letters A, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KHA&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HA&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RA&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VA&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_a-ten_tokuzan_.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stroke is known in Japanese as 命点 &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;life mark&amp;#8221;. It
corresponds to the Chinese basic stroke 點 &lt;em&gt;diǎn&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;dot&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;, which is
encoded in Unicode as ㇔U+31D4 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CJK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STROKE&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to conduct much research into the meaning of
Siddham &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt;, but I have a hunch that it embodies the phonetic
power of a character. I would theorize that the philosophy behind the
&lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; arose as a way of explaining the absence of a mark for the
inherent vowel. All Indic vowels have both independent and dependent
forms, except for the letter A, which has only an independent form.
This raises several questions from a philosophical angle: How does one
capture this inherent sound, which is part of the graphical structure
of each consonant letter, but which is unmarked? Is it contained
somehow in the letter form? If so, where in the glyph does it reside?
As it represents the initial brush stroke used for writing the vowel
letter A, it may be said to contain the graphical and phonetic essence
of the&amp;nbsp;letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I raise the issue of the Siddham &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; because it is significant
from an ideographic perspective, as are the other elemental strokes
identified in pedagogical texts. I am currently investigating the
potential of encoding these elemental strokes, which I mentioned in my
Siddham proposal as being out of scope for the basic encoding. I
welcome any information on the &lt;em&gt;myō-ten&lt;/em&gt; from users familiar with its
philosophical interpretations and its use in Siddham&amp;nbsp;pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="siddham"/></entry><entry><title>Siddham nukta: a curious innovation</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-11-05-siddham-nukta.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-05T09:58:42.109000-08:00</published><updated>2013-11-05T09:58:42.109000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-11-05:/unicode/posts/2013-11-05-siddham-nukta.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Usage of a modern Indic diacritic in&amp;nbsp;Siddham&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The combining sign  ़   &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; is used in Indic scripts for transcribing sounds
for which distinct characters do not natively exist in a writing
system. The name of the character is derived from the Arabic word نقطة
&lt;em&gt;nuqṭah&lt;/em&gt; (simplified in Indic romanization as &lt;em&gt;nukta&lt;/em&gt;)
&amp;#8220;dot&amp;#8221;. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; is used in Devanagari and related scripts of northern
India for expressing sounds not commonly used in Indo-Aryan languages,
mostly those that originate from Arabic and Persian. It is also used
natively in scripts such as Bengali and Tirhuta for distinguishing
between characters that have nearly identical graphical structures.
Although now used quite frequently in modern Indic scripts, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt;
is not part of the traditional character repertoire based upon the
representation of Sanskrit phonology. As one might expect, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt;
is not attested in historical Siddham materials as the usage of
Siddham is largely restricted to the representation of&amp;nbsp;Sanskrit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was, therefore, surprised when, during research for my
proposal to encode the script in Unicode, I stumbled across the 
&lt;a href="http://www.mandalar.com/BonjiDigitalDictionarySAMPLE/member/_Tattoo/00Tattoo.html"&gt;following sample&lt;/a&gt; 
at the &lt;a href="http://www.mandalar.com"&gt;Mandalar&lt;/a&gt; site 
showing usage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in Siddham text&amp;nbsp;as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_nukta_mandalar_tattoo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above excerpt provides the
translation or transliteration of English &amp;#8220;tattoo&amp;#8221; in Sanskrit,
English/Hindi, and Japanese. The Sanskrit वेध &lt;em&gt;vedha&lt;/em&gt; does
not truly translate as &amp;#8220;tattoo&amp;#8221;, but carries the connotation of a
&amp;#8220;piercing&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;puncturing&amp;#8221;, or &amp;#8220;perforation&amp;#8221; (√ व्यध्); the
English/Hindi ततू  &lt;em&gt;tatū&lt;/em&gt; is simply a transliteration of English &amp;#8220;tattoo&amp;#8221;
(which also might be rendered टैटू &lt;em&gt;ṭaiṭū,&lt;/em&gt; using retroflex
letters instead of dentals); and इरेज़ुमि &lt;em&gt;irezumi&lt;/em&gt;, which
is the transliteration into Siddham of the Japanese word for &amp;#8220;tattoo&amp;#8221;,
入れ墨 &lt;em&gt;irezumi&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_nukta_mandalar_tattoo_irezumi.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of interest is the usage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in
writing the word इरेज़ुमि. In general, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; is written with a
letter that has the closest phonetic proximity to the target sound.
Here, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; is combined with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIDDHAM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JA&lt;/span&gt; (/ʤ/) for
representing /z/. When &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; occurs with a consonant to which a vowel
sign is attached, then it is ordered in encoded text immediately after
the consonant and before the combining vowel sign: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JA&lt;/span&gt; + &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; + &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VOWEL&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIGN&lt;/span&gt; U. The positioning
of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; with regard to the base letter depends upon the shape of
the letter and the presence of any below-base vowel&amp;nbsp;signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandalar site has a &lt;a href="http://www.mandalar.com/DisplayJ/Bonji/index2.html"&gt;chart&lt;/a&gt;
that shows the usage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; with other consonants for representing
fricatives and other&amp;nbsp;sounds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_nukta_consonants_mandalar.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in Siddham is a
surprising innovation. I have yet to investigate the issue fully, but
at first glimpse the usage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; suggests that modern users of
Siddham seek to extend the script by adopting features used in Indic
scripts. Such borrowings show that Siddham is quite alive in Japan and
that its usage is continually being extended beyond traditional
contexts. Indeed, the Mandalar site displays these innovations under
the banner of 現代悉曇 &lt;em&gt;gendai shittan&lt;/em&gt; or &amp;#8220;modern&amp;nbsp;Siddham&amp;#8221;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_mandalar_gendai_shittan.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to support such usage, I
proposed the character for encoding as U+115C0 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIDDHAM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIGN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt;. It
corresponds to characters such as U+093C &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEVANAGARI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIGN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; and
possesses the same&amp;nbsp;properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am curious to know the
history of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in Siddham and the rationale of the &lt;em&gt;gendai shittan&lt;/em&gt; 
user(s) who first used &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in the script. Was the idea motivated
by the usage of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NUKTA&lt;/span&gt; in modern Indic orthographies? Was it influenced
by Unicode? Does the &amp;#8216;dot&amp;#8217; have ideographic&amp;nbsp;interpretations?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="siddham"/></entry><entry><title>Siddham ornaments: beyond punctuation</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-11-04-siddham-ornaments.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-04T17:10:41.817000-08:00</published><updated>2013-11-04T17:10:41.817000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-11-04:/unicode/posts/2013-11-04-siddham-ornaments.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes on ornamental signs used in&amp;nbsp;Siddham&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Siddham has several characters that are used in manuscripts for marking the 
end of text sections. Some of these are shown in column ⑦&amp;nbsp;below: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_section_marks_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palaeographically, these section marks are similar to characters in other 
Indic scripts, such as 𑁍 U+1104D &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BRAHMI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PUNCTUATION&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOTUS&lt;/span&gt;, which are ornamental 
marks. In general, these marks do not possess phonetic values or semantic 
meaning beyond their function as terminations. However, as the above excerpt 
shows, in the Japanese analysis of Siddham, these marks additionally represent 
the syllable&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;aṃ&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extant sources contain several other ornaments beyond the three
shown above. My research identified at least 14, which I &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n4336.pdf"&gt;proposed for
inclusion&lt;/a&gt; in the
Siddham&amp;nbsp;block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_section_marks_proposed.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The section marks may be classified into five groups based upon their
graphical&amp;nbsp;structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to their representation of &amp;#8220;aṃ&amp;#8221;, according to certain Japanese 
Buddhist traditions, these marks have esoteric connotations that offer 
insights into the textual passages after which they are written. Moreover, 
the graphical structure indicates other philosophical meanings, of which I 
am not fully aware or to which I am not privy! These characters would be 
considered ornaments or glyphic variants of a basic set of section marks 
according to the character-glyph model of Unicode, but on account of the 
semantics they possess beyond their function as punctuation, they have been 
encoded&amp;nbsp;independently. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="siddham"/></entry><entry><title>Siddham digits: any good evidence?</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-11-02-siddham-digits.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-11-02T01:07:47.574000-07:00</published><updated>2013-11-02T01:07:47.574000-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-11-02:/unicode/posts/2013-11-02-siddham-digits.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Notes on the status of digits in&amp;nbsp;Siddham&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I conducted research for my &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n4294.pdf"&gt;proposal to encode
Siddham&lt;/a&gt; in Unicode,
I began to notice that the primary and secondary sources I examined
all lacked a set of characters that are typically found in related
Indic scripts that emerged during the 10th&amp;nbsp;century&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this is not entirely true. As I discussed in section 3.13 of the
proposal, Siddham contains two characters, that based upon their form
and function, appear to be the remaining representatives of a set of
digits that were once likely part of the script. These characters
correspond to a palaeographic form of an Indic digit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TWO&lt;/span&gt;. But, in
Siddham this sign has lost its numeric value and it lives on only
graphically. Well, this is not entirely true, either. The sign may
have lost its numeric value, but the vestigial character retains its
numerical semantics in its function. This character is the repetition
mark shown&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/siddham_repetition_mark_example.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sign in question appears twice in the excerpt (middle row,
characters 3 and 4 from the left) and is transliterated as &amp;#8220;hūṃ&amp;#8221;. This
gloss is slightly misleading. The character itself does not represent
the syllable &amp;#8220;hūṃ&amp;#8221;; rather, it represents a &amp;#8216;ditto&amp;#8217; mark. Moreover,
although it is graphically based upon a palaeographic digit &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TWO&lt;/span&gt;, it
simply indicates that the word or syllable that precedes it is to be
repeated; not twice, but just once. The two instances of the mark mean
that &amp;#8220;hūṃ&amp;#8221; is to be recited three times, as shown. It appears that the
editor of the original text provided the intended reading instead of
&amp;#8216;ditto&amp;#8217; for the sake of&amp;nbsp;clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Siddham repetition mark corresponds glyphically to Devanagari
digit two (२), but more so to the Gurmukhi digit two (੨). It seems
that as Siddhamatrika made its way from south to east Asia, the
Buddhist scribes and scholars who used it slowly discarded from the
script features that they didn&amp;#8217;t really find necessary or useful. So,
away went the digits 0-1 and 3-9. The digit two (੨) seems to have
struck someone as a handy way of indicating a &amp;#8220;doubling&amp;#8221; when writing
or copying texts. So, what we have now in Siddham is essentially an
east Asian ideographic interpretation of an Indic character that was
originally and palaeographically a sign for a digit. The &amp;#8216;੨&amp;#8217; is the
only numerical sign that I have seen in Siddham&amp;nbsp;texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that is not entirely true either&amp;#8230; In the latter stages of my
research I found the following chart on a Japanese&amp;nbsp;site:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/bonji_numerals_mandalar.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These &amp;#8220;Bonji numerals&amp;#8221; appear to be modern creations based upon
Devanagari digits. I submitted a
&lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n4467.pdf"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; to encode
a set of digits in the Siddham block based upon these signs, but the
Unicode Technical Committee (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UTC&lt;/span&gt;) requested additional evidence of the
use of digits in the&amp;nbsp;script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does anyone know of Siddham manuscripts, pedagogical texts, or other
records that contain examples of digits? Hmmm, at this point, I may
even accept 入れ墨 &lt;em&gt;irezumi&lt;/em&gt; as evidence, even if the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UTC&lt;/span&gt; might&amp;nbsp;not!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="siddham"/></entry><entry><title>A distinctive Khojki letter for qa?</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-10-12-khojki-qa.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-10-12T19:40:36.542000-08:00</published><updated>2013-10-12T19:40:36.542000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-10-12:/unicode/posts/2013-10-12-khojki-qa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is a character used for /q/ a distinctive letter or a glyphic&amp;nbsp;variant?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following excerpt from a printed Khojki book contains two forms of
&lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; highlighted in blue is the representative glyph of
U+11208 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KHOJKI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KA&lt;/span&gt; (to be published in Unicode 7), while the red
&lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; is the alternate&amp;nbsp;form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/khojki_ka_variant.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- _kalā̃m_ --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the red &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; is used in the word &lt;em&gt;kalām&lt;/em&gt;, while the blue &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; is
used in the word &lt;em&gt;kalāṃm&lt;/em&gt;, both are representations
of the Arabic word کلام &lt;em&gt;kalām&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;composition, work&amp;#8221;; the &lt;em&gt;anusvāra&lt;/em&gt; in
&lt;em&gt;kalāṃm&lt;/em&gt; is not semantically&amp;nbsp;significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternate form is used in other sources for representing &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt;,
suggesting that the red &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; is a glyphic&amp;nbsp;variant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/asani_1992_p283_variant_ka.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it also appears in other source, where it is used for
representing &lt;em&gt;qa&lt;/em&gt; (the Arabic ق &lt;em&gt;qāf&lt;/em&gt;), suggesting that it may indeed
be a distinctive letter, a possible *&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KHOJKI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QA&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/asani_1992_p294_qaf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not yet seen this work, so I do not know the context in which
the letter is used for &lt;em&gt;qāf&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shape of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KHOJKI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KA&lt;/span&gt; is fairly uniform across printed
materials and manuscripts. It is of interest that both forms occur in
the same document, as shown in the first image, and in such close
proximity. The excerpt is from a printed book and is likely a faithful
reproduction of a manuscript. Analysis of several manuscript sources
is necessary in order to determine whether the red &lt;em&gt;ka&lt;/em&gt; is a glyphic
variant of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KA&lt;/span&gt; or a distinct Khojki letter &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="khojki"/></entry><entry><title>A Graphite font for Khojki</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-10-10-khojki-graphite.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-10-10T00:05:32.506000-07:00</published><updated>2013-10-10T00:05:32.506000-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-10-10:/unicode/posts/2013-10-10-khojki-graphite.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A Graphite font for&amp;nbsp;Khojki&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in 
&lt;a href="2013-10-09-script-encoding-paradox.html"&gt;&amp;#8220;The Imminent Paradox of New Scripts in Unicode&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, 
I have begun to develop Graphite fonts for several of the historical and minor scripts
that I have proposed for inclusion in the Unicode Standard. The first
of these fonts is for Khojki, which I 
&lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n3978.pdf"&gt;proposed for encoding&lt;/a&gt; in Unicode a few
years ago and will likely appear in The Unicode Standard, version 7.0,
planned for release in&amp;nbsp;2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khojki is a medieval Indic script from the Sindh region, situated in
present day Pakistan, which is used for liturgical purposes by the
Nizari Ismaili community. It has been preserved by this minority
community for six centuries, both at home and in their diaspora. The
script has been used since the 15th century for manuscripts and since
the early 20th century for the printing of books. There are
organizations, such as the &lt;a href="http://www.iis.ac.uk/"&gt;Institute of Ismaili
Studies&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IIS&lt;/span&gt;) in London, which possesses a
large collection of materials in Khojki, and several scholars
worldwide that conduct research on these materials, that will benefit
from this&amp;nbsp;effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed this font on a volunteer basis to meet the needs of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IIS&lt;/span&gt;, which has a requirement for the input and display Unicode Khojki
in order to carry out their cataloguing efforts. The font, named
KhojkiGraphite, is based upon the KhojkiJiwa font designed by Pyarali
Jiwa of the United Kingdom years ago. Mr. Jiwa&amp;#8217;s font is the only
TrueType font for Khojki; however is it based upon a legacy encoding.
Its glyph repertoire contains several consonant-vowel ligatures;
however, there are several inconsistencies with these glyph. I&amp;#8217;ve
edited the glyphs to bring them into structural and optical alignment,
fixed metrics, and added Graphite rendering rules in order to create
the first Unicode-encoded Khojki font. At present it works in
OpenOffice and LibreOffice, in XeLaTeX and XeLaTeX, as well as in
other applications that support&amp;nbsp;Graphite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt of a &lt;em&gt;ginān&lt;/em&gt; typed in LibreOffice using&amp;nbsp;KhojkiGraphite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/khojki_graphite_specimen.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to provide users with an effective means of using the font,
Wafi Momin of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IIS&lt;/span&gt; has developed a basic keyboard using the Microsoft
Keyboard Layout Creator (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MSKLC&lt;/span&gt;). So far, the combination of the font
and the keyboard is helping &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IIS&lt;/span&gt; to carry out its projects using modern
technologies and to make their materials available in digital media
using common&amp;nbsp;standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will release the KhojkiGraphite font and keyboard for public testing
in the next few months. My goal is to release the package in
conjunction with the publication of Unicode 7.0, so that users have
immediate support for Khojki, even though in limited&amp;nbsp;environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="khojki"/></entry><entry><title>The paradox of encoding new scripts in Unicode</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-10-09-script-encoding-paradox.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-10-09T00:09:18.590000-08:00</published><updated>2013-10-09T00:09:18.590000-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-10-09:/unicode/posts/2013-10-09-script-encoding-paradox.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The need for full support for each Unicode&amp;nbsp;version.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past several years I have developed Unicode standards for
numerous historical and minor
&lt;a href="http://pandey.github.io/unicode"&gt;scripts&lt;/a&gt; of South Asia. Some of my
formally proposed encodings have been approved and are making 
their way through various stages of balloting as part of the
process established by the International Organization for
Standardization (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;) &amp;#8212;- Unicode is also known as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IEC&lt;/span&gt; 10646 &amp;#8212;-
while others have been formally published in the&amp;nbsp;standard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inclusion of a script in Unicode is a major milestone. Native user and
scholarly communities await the arrival of these new encodings from
the day that I contact them &amp;#8212;- if not for years in the making &amp;#8212;- 
and discuss my plans for developing an encoding for a particular script. 
It takes nearly two years for an encoding to be published in Unicode after 
being approved by both the Unicode Technical Committee and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WG2&lt;/span&gt; group. 
But, once a script is in Unicode the general perception of what &amp;#8220;inclusion
in the standard&amp;#8221; means is far removed from the reality that is
suggested by such an&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;inclusion&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disjunction between expectation and reality is truly a paradox: The
encoding of a script in Unicode does not automatically imply that it will be
supported out of the box. As is the case with other historical and minor scripts
encoded in Unicode, it is unlikely that major software houses will
rush to provide support for these scripts right away, or if they do so
at&amp;nbsp;all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these companies do not implement support for these scripts,
users will be unable to produce documents in their writing systems 
using common applications such as Microsoft Word and Adobe InDesign. Users 
will be unable to view websites containing text in these scripts using 
Internet Explorer, Firefox, and other browsers. Moreover, typographers 
wishing to design new, modern typefaces for these scripts will be hampered 
because their creations will be unusable in ubiquitous platforms such as Windows.
The reason for this is that OpenType, the common font standard, is
dependent upon Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Uniscribe rendering engine and a font will
not work in Windows until Uniscribe can handle the underlying script.
Certainly, those who use Linux systems can rely on HarfBuzz, an open
source OpenType rendering engine; but, ultimately, from a practical
perspective, Uniscribe support is important because Windows is the
most-commonly used operating system&amp;nbsp;worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What good is a Unicode standard for a script if there is no way for
the general public to actually make use of it? What good is a Unicode
standard for a script if implementation of it is dependent upon the
economic cost-benefit decisions of major software companies? Although
historical and minority scripts and related linguistic ecologies may
not be profit generators, they are certainly valuable from humanist&amp;nbsp;perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is the reality if Microsoft, Apple, Google, and others don&amp;#8217;t support 
historical and minor scripts in their operating systems when a new
version of the Unicode standard is published&amp;#8230; or ever? For now,
thankfully, there we can provide font solutions using the Graphite
rendering engine developed by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIL&lt;/span&gt;. However, Graphite fonts are not
supported in Windows and, therefore, will not work in Microsoft
Office, Internet Explorer, and other commonly-used applications.
Applications like LibreOffice and XeTeX support Graphite, but the user
base for these is limited. In the end, at least Graphite exists and
those of us who work with lesser-used writing systems owe gratitude to
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIL&lt;/span&gt; for having the foresight and imagination to provide a means for
rendering writing systems independent of the whims of software&amp;nbsp;house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I maintain the hope that Microsoft will continue to expand Uniscribe
in order to support all scripts in the Unicode standard. But until the
time comes when there is mandatory synchronization between releases of
the standard and implementation, we must turn to other, albeit
limited, solutions. As part of this solution, I will build Graphite
fonts for all the scripts I have brought into Unicode in order to
provide a basic level of support for these scripts in the Windows
environment, even if the range of usage is limited. I am not a
professional typopgrapher nor do I pretend to be, but such efforts are
just an extension of the work I&amp;#8217;ve&amp;nbsp;started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I am an individual with limited resources and numerous
constraints. I encourage Microsoft, Apple, Google and others to meet me half way.
After all, what good is a standard if no one cares to support&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/></entry><entry><title>Fraction signs in Oriya</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2013-05-08-oriya-fraction-signs.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2013-05-08T11:19:00-08:00</published><updated>2013-05-08T11:19:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2013-05-08:/unicode/posts/2013-05-08-oriya-fraction-signs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Six fraction signs historically used in Oriya have been included in
Unicode 6.0. These characters appear in written and printed documents,
and were part of at least four different sets of Oriya metal fonts.
The fraction signs were commonly used until 1958, at which time the
Government of India …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Six fraction signs historically used in Oriya have been included in
Unicode 6.0. These characters appear in written and printed documents,
and were part of at least four different sets of Oriya metal fonts.
The fraction signs were commonly used until 1958, at which time the
Government of India adopted the decimal system for currency and the
metric system for weights and measures. The characters are now&amp;nbsp;obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fraction signs are illustrated by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;R. J.&lt;/span&gt; Grundy in the &lt;span
style="font-style:italic;"&gt;Concise Oriya-English Dictionary&lt;/span&gt;
(Cuttack: Orissa Mission Press,&amp;nbsp;1928):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/oriya_fractions_grundy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amos Sutton shows only the quarter fractions in the &lt;span
style="font-style:italic;"&gt;Introductory Grammar of the Oriya
Language&lt;/span&gt; (Cuttack: Baptist Mission Press,&amp;nbsp;1831):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/oriya_fractions_sutton.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These fraction signs are now part of the &lt;a
href="http://www.unicode.org/charts/PDF/U0B00.pdf"&gt;Oriya block&lt;/a&gt; in&amp;nbsp;Unicode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/oriya_fractions_unicode.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Oriya fractions are related to the &amp;#8216;currency numerator&amp;#8217; signs used
in Bengali for writing&amp;nbsp;fractions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/oriya_fractions_comp.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the Oriya fraction signs is available in the 
&lt;a href="http://www.dkuug.dk/jtc1/sc2/wg2/docs/n3471.pdf"&gt;original proposal to encode these signs&lt;/a&gt;. 
Information about the &amp;#8216;Common Indic&amp;#8217; fraction signs shown
in the above image may be found in the 
&lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/jtc1/sc2/wg2/docs/n3367.pdf"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; 
to encode &amp;#8216;Common Indic Number Forms&amp;#8217; in&amp;nbsp;Unicode.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="oriya"/></entry><entry><title>Signs for representing Kashmiri vowels in Sharada</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2011-05-12-sharada-kashmiri-signs.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2011-05-12T12:31:00-07:00</published><updated>2011-05-12T12:31:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2011-05-12:/unicode/posts/2011-05-12-sharada-kashmiri-signs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Innovations for Kashmiri vowels in&amp;nbsp;Sharada&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Sharada script was used primarily for writing Sanskrit. In order
to represent Kashmiri, three additional signs were added to the&amp;nbsp;script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A below-base slash that resembles the Devanagari &lt;em&gt;virāma&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/sharada_kashmiri_slash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An above-base bar that represents the Devanagari &lt;em&gt;anudatta&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/sharada_kashmiri_bar.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An underdot that is similar to the Devanagari &lt;em&gt;nukta&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/sharada_kashmiri_underdot.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently researching these signs. Please contact me if you have
information about the use of these signs for writing&amp;nbsp;Kashmiri.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="sharada"/></entry><entry><title>Change of block name: ‘Sindhi’ to ‘Khudawadi’</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2011-01-30-sindhi-name-change.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2011-01-30T14:48:00-08:00</published><updated>2011-01-30T14:48:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2011-01-30:/unicode/posts/2011-01-30-sindhi-name-change.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Details on change of proposed block name to&amp;nbsp;Khudawadi&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My work on the Landa-based scripts of Sindhi continues. However, there
has been a &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/jtc1/sc2/wg2/docs/n3957.pdf"&gt;change&lt;/a&gt;
to the name of the &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217; script that I proposed, and which I
briefly discussed in &lt;a
href="http://anshumanpandey.blogspot.com/2010/08/standard-sindhi-script.html"&gt;a
post in August 2010&lt;/a&gt;. The script is now called &amp;#8220;Khudawadi&amp;#8221;. An
image of it is given&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/grierson_khudawadi_excerpt.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Khudawadi script was initially proposed under named &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217;
because its character repertoire is based upon the &amp;#8216;Standard Sindhi&amp;#8217;
script. Standard Sindhi is itself based upon the Khudawadi script,
which was the most well-known and complete of the Landa-based scripts
used in Sindh. The intent of the &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n3871.pdf"&gt;original
proposal&lt;/a&gt; was to
develop a standard that might also be used for representing the minor
Landa scripts of Sindh, some of which are unsuitable for independent
encoding. As &amp;#8216;Standard Sindhi&amp;#8217; was developed from Khudawadi in the
1860s with the same idea, the rationale is valid, but the choice of
the name &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217; is&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generic name &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217; is problematic for several reasons. It is
generally used for referring to the class of Landa-based scripts of
Sindh, ie. the &amp;#8216;Sindhi scripts&amp;#8217;. It is not the proper name of any
writing system that belongs to this script family. In fact, several
other scripts, such as Khojki and Shikarpuri, are also known as
&amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217;. Even &amp;#8216;Standard Sindhi&amp;#8217; was not known by the generic name
&amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217;, but as &amp;#8216;Hindi Sindhi&amp;#8217;, etc. In modern India and Pakistan,
the &amp;#8216;Sindhi script&amp;#8217; is commonly understood to be the Arabic-based
script used for writing the Sindhi&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name &amp;#8216;Khudawadi&amp;#8217; is the most appropriate name for the script. It
is the proper name of the script and is well attested in primary and
secondary literature, such as the &lt;em&gt;Linguistic Survey of India&lt;/em&gt;. The
name is also used for &amp;#8216;Standard Sindhi&amp;#8217;, which is a reformed variant
of Khudawadi and is referred to as such, ie. &amp;#8216;improved Khudawadi&amp;#8217;, in
various&amp;nbsp;sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change of name from &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217; to &amp;#8216;Khudawadi&amp;#8217; will provide greater
semantic and taxonomic clarity in identifying the various scripts used
for writing Sindhi and the scripts used in Sindh. For example, it is
more appropriate to refer to &amp;#8220;the Sindhi scripts &amp;#8216;Khudawadi&amp;#8217; and
&amp;#8216;Khojki&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;, rather than to &amp;#8220;the Sindhi scripts &amp;#8216;Sindhi&amp;#8217; and &amp;#8216;Khojki&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;.
Moreover, the use of the name &amp;#8216;Khudawadi&amp;#8217; will enable users to
distinguish between the Landa-based and Arabic-based&amp;nbsp;scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details are available in the
&lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/jtc1/sc2/wg2/docs/n3957.pdf"&gt;document&lt;/a&gt; requesting
the formal change of name. The final proposal for Khudawadi is almost
ready for submission to the Unicode Technical&amp;nbsp;Committee.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="khudawadi"/></entry><entry><title>Alternate letter for ḍa in Devanagari</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2010-12-10-devanagari-dda.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-12-10T16:22:00-08:00</published><updated>2010-12-10T16:22:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2010-12-10:/unicode/posts/2010-12-10-devanagari-dda.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another letter for writing a retroflex stop in&amp;nbsp;Devanagari&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Devanagari, the phoneme [ɖ] is generally represented with ड U+0921
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEVANAGARI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDA&lt;/span&gt;. In historical Devanagari orthography for the
Marwari language of Rajasthan, [ɖ] is represented with a different
letter. In Marwari, ड is instead used for representing [ɽ], an
allographic variant of [ɖ], which is generally written in Hindi as ड़
U+095C &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DEVANAGARI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDDHA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Linguistic Survey of India&lt;/em&gt;, George Grierson describes the
usage of these characters in Marwari, as shown in the image&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/grierson_marwari_dda.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character is also shown by Mathias Metzger (&lt;em&gt;Die Sprache der
Vakīl-Briefe aus Rājasthān&lt;/em&gt;, Würzburg: Ergon Verlag,&amp;nbsp;2003):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/metzger_retroflexes.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Marwari &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDA&lt;/span&gt; cannot be treated as a glyphic variant of ड and
should be encoded as an independent letter. I have submitted a
&lt;a href="http://www.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n3970.pdf"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;, which
contains additional information about the letter and examples of&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forms shown by Grierson and Metzger differ slightly. My attempt at
representing the two forms, in adherence with Monotype Devanagari, is
shown&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/marwari_dda_glyphs.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently learned that this letter was also used in Devanagari orthography 
for languages of Sindh. The following specimen shows use of 
the letter in&amp;nbsp;Kutchi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/kutchi_dda_color.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its usage contrasts with the regular letter &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDA&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/kutchi_dda_gray.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be interested to learn if &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MARWARI&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LETTER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDA&lt;/span&gt; is used in the 
orthographies for other&amp;nbsp;languages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="devanagari"/></entry><entry><title>An inscription in the Khudawadi script</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2010-09-01-khudawadi-inscription.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-09-01T13:13:00-07:00</published><updated>2010-09-01T13:13:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2010-09-01:/unicode/posts/2010-09-01-khudawadi-inscription.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Details on an inscription bearing text in&amp;nbsp;Khudawadi&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/JTC1/SC2/WG2/docs/n3766.pdf"&gt;Landa-based scripts of
Sindh&lt;/a&gt; were generally
not used for much more than routine writing and general commercial
activity. Michel Boivin of L&amp;#8217;École des hautes études en sciences
sociales (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EHESS&lt;/span&gt;), Paris, recently sent me photographs that show the
use of the Khudawadi script in an&amp;nbsp;inscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a photograph of a Khudawadi inscription in an &lt;em&gt;ex-voto&lt;/em&gt; at
the shrine of &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=odero+lal+sindh+pakistan&amp;amp;sll=25.698903,68.561978&amp;amp;sspn=0.020302,0.038581&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=Odero+Lal+Village,+Matiari,+Sindh,+Pakistan&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;ll=25.700938,68.565674&amp;amp;spn=5.195627,9.876709&amp;amp;z=7"&gt;Udero Lal in Hyderabad,
Sindh&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/khudawadi_exvotos_udero_lal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image below shows the detail of the Khudawadi&amp;nbsp;inscription:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/khudawadi_exvotos_udero_lal_detail.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to Khudawadi, this &lt;em&gt;ex-voto&lt;/em&gt; has inscriptions in four
other scripts: Latin, Devanagari, Arabic, and&amp;nbsp;Gurmukhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A proposal to encode Khudawadi in the Unicode standard is being&amp;nbsp;prepared.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="khudawadi"/></entry><entry><title>Forms of candrabindu in Sharada</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2010-08-31-sharada-candrabindu.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-08-31T03:03:00-07:00</published><updated>2010-08-31T03:03:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2010-08-31:/unicode/posts/2010-08-31-sharada-candrabindu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Varying representations of candrabindu in&amp;nbsp;Sharada&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The regular form ? of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt; in Sharada resembles 
an inverted form of Devanagari ?. Several Sharada manuscripts 
show an inverted form of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt;, which co-occurs with 
the regular form, sometimes on the same line.
In the following image, the inverted &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt; sign is used for
writing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt;, while the regular &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt; is used in other&amp;nbsp;contexts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/sharada_candrabindus_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above specimen might lead one to think that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt; is written with an
inverted &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt;. Is it perhaps because it is considered a
&amp;#8216;special&amp;#8217;&amp;nbsp;symbol?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following image both regular and inverted &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt; are used
for writing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt; (sorry, the beginning of the second line is smudged in
the&amp;nbsp;original):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/sharada_candrabindus_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a semantic distinction between the regular and inverted forms
of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CANDRABINDU&lt;/span&gt; in Sharada? It does not seem so, especially when
considering the use of both forms in writing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OM&lt;/span&gt;, which has a fairly
fixed&amp;nbsp;meaning&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we just chalk it up to scribal&amp;nbsp;idiosyncrasy? &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="sharada"/></entry><entry><title>Modi accounting signs and number forms</title><link href="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/posts/2010-08-28-modi-accounting-signs.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-08-28T15:40:00-07:00</published><updated>2010-08-28T15:40:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Anshuman Pandey</name></author><id>tag:pandey.github.io,2010-08-28:/unicode/posts/2010-08-28-modi-accounting-signs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Signs used for numerical notation in&amp;nbsp;Modi&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before the standardization of currency and monetary units 
that followed the formation of the Republic of India 
and other nation states in South Asia in the middle of 
the 20th century, various forms of numerical notation 
were used in the&amp;nbsp;region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modi documents contain unique signs that are used for marking monetary
amounts. Two such signs are shown in the image&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/modi_number_forms.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character ꠷ is called आळी  &lt;em&gt;āḷī&lt;/em&gt; in Marathi. It represents
the absence of numbers and is written after whole amounts to indicate
that there are no fractions. In the image, the first highlighted
example is ८००꠷ &amp;#8216;800/-&amp;#8216; and the third is १४०꠷ &amp;#8216;140/-&amp;#8216;. The ꠷ sign is
encoded in Unicode as U+A837 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NORTH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INDIC&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLACEHOLDER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MARK&lt;/span&gt;. (More
information on this and other signs is provided in my &lt;a href="http://std.dkuug.dk/jtc1/sc2/wg2/docs/n3367.pdf"&gt;proposal to
encode Common Indic number&amp;nbsp;forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other sign shown resembles the ÷ &amp;#8216;division sign&amp;#8217; or &lt;em&gt;obelus&lt;/em&gt;. It
is used in the highlighted examples two and four in the above image.
Based upon the context in which it is used, it could represent a
&amp;#8216;remainder&amp;#8217; sign, eg. the amount written and then some; or a 
&lt;em&gt;pāvalī&lt;/em&gt; `quarter&amp;#8217;. &lt;!-- .|. --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://pandey.github.io/unicode/images/modi_pavali.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is anyone who is familiar with the use of these signs in
Modi, I would be happy to hear from&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="unicode"/><category term="modi"/></entry></feed>